ok let's get started so the theme of
this week is talking about optimizing
the assembly output we create so can we
take these programs that we have as
input and on their way to the resulting
assembly can we do intelligent things to
avoid either generating so many
instructions or can we generate smarter
instructions use less memory all these
kinds of things and so today I want to
talk about three ideas there's sort of
three different ideas that fall into
three different categories of compiler
optimization there are three sort of
little ideas on the surface that if you
wanted to put in lots of detailed work
or write the GCC team wanted to put in
years of detailed work you can see a
trajectory spanning out of how you'd put
more and more effort into this thing to
make things really really good in 131 we
don't have hundreds of thousands of men
and women hours to put into our
compilers that's what goes into a
compiler like GCC it has lots of
thinking about many many different cases
so we're going to talk about some
interesting cases today across a few
different kinds of compiler
optimizations we might try and these are
actually quite similar to things that
GCC does but one of the first things
we're going to talk about actually the
first two things are things that GCC
does in particular so what I have on the
screen here is on the left-hand side I
just copied the code that we have in our
reference implementation for ii-if from
like cobra and Diamondback and it's
doing what if needs to do it compiles
the conditional expression here called
if exper checks if it's a boolean
because in our
our language we care about these being
bully ins and then it has the code for
the then branch and the code for the
else branch and it checks for trueness
too so what I have on the right-hand
side is a more detailed pattern match on
e if then is on the left-hand side a
more detailed pattern match than what's
on the left-hand side so this left hand
side match will match programs that look
like if X then some II 1 LC 2 they'll
match things that look like if some
function call on some value so match any
possible if expression that we could
write an e if expression you write if
you parse it turn it into the abstract
syntax and match it against that case
it'll match and that's what will compile
for it this right hand case is only
going to match if expressions that look
like keep the names the same here with
some expression and then in else
possession it's only going to match
things whoops a greater not less it's
only going to match things where the
thing in conditional position has a
greater than sign first question can you
talk about what might be something we
could do better if we knew we were
matching against this case if we knew
that we were only matching ifs against
this case where we had a greater than
what could we do better what could we do
that would be smarter than the
instructions we're generating for if in
all the generic cases like what this
just for 30 seconds or so what could we
do that would be smarter on the
right-hand side
there's no talking talk about it talk
about it talk about it talk talk
okay ideas there's a few different ideas
in this space but ideas ideas if we have
this extra information what can we maybe
do better what are some ideas I see
nodding idea if oh so you're saying if
we know something about a 1 and a 2 so
let's imagine let's get even more
specific right you're saying another
idea so I'm just gonna put a dotted line
here so we know that we're talking about
something more specific but if we wanted
to talk about things where one or more
of these was numbers then in this case
in this case we could say well we're
definitely just need the instructions
for the else branch because this is
always gonna evaluate to false right
that's what you're getting at right
right so if we knew even more right
there's a more detailed match I could
write where instead of having a e1 and
e2 here I could write something like
what if these are both numbers right
that's an idea it's a cool idea that we
might use actually gonna use the idea
related to that later in a later in the
lecture but what about if we don't know
anything more still about a 1 in E -
yeah can save a boolean check Y please
can we save a boolean check ok maybe we
can save a boolean check other ideas
what's that also potentially save a
branch also potentially save a branch so
ideas of saving boolean check saving a
branch we'll come back to those other
ideas other ideas
okay I'm gonna come back and say why can
we skip the boolean check why is that
okay yeah what if there's like an error
what if you wanna need to cause an error
then how do I know yeah so greater than
either II 1 or e 2 produces an error or
their non numbers so greater than
produces an error in which case the
program's done we don't need to worry
about the answer for this sub expression
because we got an error right and this
would be true in many languages right in
Java you would no longer worry about the
answer for this sub expression and an if
if an exception was thrown some
exception handlers gonna handle that you
don't have to worry about it locally
here so greater than always returns a
boolean always puts a boolean in EAX as
long as it succeeds and we don't have to
worry about the failure case because the
code we're generating here isn't the
code for that isn't the code that
handles errors so we know since we know
that the results of greater then must be
a boolean we don't need this entire test
bool chunk this part of inserting the
code for test pool and where we add it
in the list here
these don't need to be part of this
match
if we were just thinking about moving
the code over and implementing this
match case over here now we're still
gonna have to do some stuff that has to
do with the if and the then and the else
and things like that to compile those
sub expressions but we don't need to
test pool you had suggested that we
could get rid of a branch case to was a
suggestion from the middle what was the
branch case you're suggesting we could
get rid of if we implement greater than
with branch oh so are you saying we like
inside the greater than operation there
might be a branch in there and we can
make that branch do the if thing instead
so maybe we could get clever with
compiling the greater than at this sort
of at the same time as the if right so
there'd be some opportunities there okay
so maybe we could go deeper into
exploring that option the the point I
had in mind when I put this up that's an
interesting idea I didn't have that idea
in mind when I picked this example the
main thing I had in mind when I picked
this example is pointing out this bool
case that we can get rid of this boolean
check by virtue of the fact that we know
that if we're doing a greater in if in
the conditional position it's gonna
produce a boolean so there's no need to
check there's no way that omitting this
code could cause this program to have a
different answer or have an error when
there wasn't an error before etc it's
gonna have the same answers so that's
pretty interesting it means that we
could write these more detailed match
cases on some expressions in the current
compilers we have this is particularly
useful in expressions that do these tag
checks for errors but there's other
cases where this can be useful as well
we can write these more detailed match
cases and do a better job of selecting
which instructions we generate for a
given expression so this site this idea
has a name I'm just gonna write it over
here this idea is called well it's
really--it's there's a huge family of
techniques here but the overall idea is
called instruction selection and this is
getting at this idea that right now
we've written sort of one case for each
expression in in our language right EF
has one case that matches it in the
compiler EBU bully num e app everything
compiler and there's only one option for
which instructions we generate for each
expression we generate it and the idea
of instruction selection is well if we
use more information about what's going
on around an expression we can do some
smarter things when we generate code
omitting omitting checks like this is
one idea so I want to talk about this
more generally but before I talk about
it more generally I want to put a few
examples up here so another set of
examples here these are nested matches
on on plus and they need some letters
and the question I want to ask is which
of these
which of these won't let us skip a tag
check right so we just saw how if we
know that the thing in conditional
position in an if is a greater than we
can skip the tag check for boolean's in
it what about this so these here's four
options of nested nested binary
operators
well this let us do this should say well
this should say EEPROM to sorry about
that just for consistency that way
five four three two one
okay there's sort of a weirdness in one
of these options so I want you to talk
about it just for 20 or 30 seconds just
talk about it briefly
okay so what's so first of all what's
the what's the answer here or at least
like the the most obvious answer here
well in B and C we're doing a plus and
then we know that the first argument is
either a number or another plus and we
know that numbers well numbers don't
need to be checked for being numbers and
we know that plus plus expressions have
to return numbers so in B and C we can
definitely omit the tag check for the
first argument we don't have to check
the tag of this expression or this
expression we can just skip it and maybe
even generate even more intelligent
instructions there in the first case in
answer a like if we have a function
application we don't know that much
locally to this pattern match about what
could possibly be returned from that
function the way we have our compiler
set up we don't know much at all about
the return values of functions until we
call them so option A it's really hard
to see how we would skip a check check
by using option a we kind of have to do
the function call see what comes back
and then do the addition with it so the
most obvious answer here is a and it's
sort of the intended answer but D is
intentionally weird B is intentionally
weird what's weird about D that's weird
about D yeah yeah yeah a one is
definitely gonna produce a boolean which
means the plus expression is definitely
going to cause an error when it runs
right this is like a known error case
right it's definitely going to cause an
error so one interesting thing about
this is wait we have a little bit of a
design decision about what to do if we
were to match on an expression that we
know is going to cause an error at
runtime according to our definition of
an optimization what should we do we
have a definition of an optimization we
gave on Monday what should we do
yeah maybe make maybe call an error
right away oh right away right away
there's this notion of time should we do
it in the compiler
would be and maybe as right away as
possible right as right away as possible
is fail with bad right let's give a
compiler definition of optimization say
about this though
well what yeah so our definition of
optimization the key part was having the
same answer and effects that was the
whoops that was the key part of our
optimization definition was that we
might generate different instructions
which might do something different in
terms of speed or memory usage but the
program we generate ought to have the
same answer and the same effects so
we're so there's a couple places where
we might have answers and effects coming
out here so and in particular one of the
places we might have interesting things
happening and they're like underscored
out right now is right here we're going
to do this greater than operation on two
expressions what if they have effects
what if they have effects what if the
programmer was expecting something to
happen there what I want you to think
about for a minute what's an example of
a program it's an example of a program
that has effects in this greater
position talk about this for me what do
I mean by that what is an example of a
program that has effects where I've
circled these two underscores for near
greater what's an example of a program
that has effects there talk about this
for a minute
okay so here's here's one of the here's
sort of one of the simpler examples I
can think of to illustrate this or at
least the shortest what if we have a
program like this
we're a program that adds the result of
greater than on printing some
expressions now this would mean that if
we ran on an unauthorized compiler this
would print one print to compare them
for greater than and then error on the
plus I thought it's what this program
would do if we ran it on the unoptimized
compiler if our optimization sort of
took that out or took out that operation
or just failed in the beginning we would
switch to the optimizing compiler and
things would just be way different than
they were our program wouldn't run if we
just failed with here and if we skipped
doing this operation because it was
known to be an error we would just see
different answers come out might see an
answer when it used to be an error so if
we're going to uphold this definition of
an optimization which I'm arguing is a
good idea we might be able to skip some
work here like we know that if greater
produces an answer we should eventually
error right so we might be able to skip
doing the actual plus because we know
this is going to produce an error but we
shouldn't completely avoid compiling
this or turn it into a compile error
that might be a design decision we make
about the language to try and report
errors like this and say now the
language is changed and reports these
kinds of errors in the compiler but we
should not have the optimizer changing
the behavior of the program the program
used to print something out when it's
optimized it should still print the same
thing okay so this overall idea this
overall idea which shows up in our
compiler as these detailed pattern
matches and using information from these
detailed pattern matches to make better
decisions
it's called instruction selection and
there's sort of a visual way to think
about it so if we take one of our if
programs from above we can think of the
programs were writing and we've done
this you can think about this for any
kind of recursive data structure like
like our abstract syntax trees and we
don't usually draw them this way in this
class but it's useful to draw them this
way sometimes so let's just a imagine
drawing this if expression out is a tree
so the ifs that we were matching on in
detail had an if at the root then a
greater than a that's a less than sign
and then a greater than on this side and
then there were two expressions and in
Noah's of an an else expression and E 1
and E 2 and then an else we can think of
as being full sub trees because those
could be whole sub expressions so the
the overall if match right the if match
that matched any possible expression we
could think of that as just handling
this node of the tree and then it
handled everything else this entire left
hand side sub tree and these two sub
trees separately and then these separate
sub trees would get broken up by other
naturals that's sort of what our
compilers are doing now every time we
look at this tree we look at one node in
the tree figure out what to do with that
one node and then recursively handle all
the sub trees better there is some
expressions our more detailed match
is picking a larger chunk of the tree at
a time to handle picking a larger chunk
of the tree at a time to handle and you
can think of everything I did above with
the plus expression this matching on the
plus expression to be different parts of
the expression starting at the root that
are matched and then recursive pieces
end up getting handled by doing
recursive calls so one of the things
you'll see in literature on instruction
selection and I'm going to not go too in
depth into this I want to point out to
you that this exists but we have finite
time in 131 1 this picture gets at this
idea in instruction selection that what
we are doing and I'm going to just move
this example down so I can get this
picture next to this picture what we are
doing when we select instructions is we
have some tree that represents our
program and we've got all of these
different ways and I'm just going to
draw them as these abstract shapes off
to the side to compile subsets of nodes
in the tree into useful assembly
instructions into useful target machine
instructions and what our compiler is
trying to do one way to view what our
compilers job is is to find a complete
covering tiling of this tree with
different ways we know how to compile
notes so there might be one tiling that
involves grabbing these with this color
grabbing these with this color grabbing
these with this color and then these
down here that might be one possible way
to think about tiling this entire tree
with ways we know to turn nodes into
instructions and if you squint at our
pattern matches you could imagine that
the the purple region here and the red
region here our nested matches where we
matched on more information and then
the bottom most leaf nodes are things
like numbers and boolean's that we just
compile very directly and the strategy
we have implemented in our compiler is a
greedy strategy that starts from the
root what our compiler does is greedily
matches things starting from the root
picking picking what it can find from
the root and in recurring on pieces and
there is an entire body of literature if
you took if you think like a graduate
course in compilers or look into deeper
compiler optimizations there's an entire
body of literature on ways of thinking
about this as a tiling problem
expressing the different ways you know
how to compile subsets of nodes and
trying to come up with an optimal tiling
of this tree and that's a an interesting
way to go forward with this a reasonably
straightforward way to implement this
and this is also related to how GCC does
this is have a bunch of handwritten
greedy rules that start at the root and
go down that's really what our pattern
matches are in the compile function and
this is what GCC does for a decent chunk
of its instruction selection and so I
just want to put this picture up here to
show you that there's this thing that
we're doing is one implementation
strategy and there's a whole sort of
graduate course in compilers you could
take talking about this people write the
dissertations on how to do clever
instruction selection but well we're we
can get pretty far with this greedy
strategy starting from the root using a
little more information
so that's instruction selection and
that's one way we can take we can see
from our existing compiler and implement
it ourselves how to do a little bit
better in generating assembly code any
questions about that idea about
high-level idea
okay so one okay so I'm gonna put up
some assembly code
I just want to highlight I actually only
want to highlight one piece of this as I
want it because I want to get through
all three ideas today so wanna highlight
just one small piece of this I mean this
is similar to the code that I had up on
Monday the piece I want to highlight is
right here and this is code that you
have probably seen in the generated code
of your compilers a lot but the pattern
that comes up over and over again
in the generated codes of our compiler
we take the value in the ax we move it
onto the stack and then we take the
value at that stack address and move it
back into EAX and and much rejoicing was
had at that extra work so there is an
extremely sort of blunt straightforward
approach to handling this kind of
problem in compiled output this is about
as I don't know about if it's worth
calling it brute force but it's like
this is a solution that is clever maybe
only in its simplicity so one way to
talk about making this better avoiding
this case and compiled output is let's
imagine writing a function called
improve instructions that takes an
instruction list and it's going to
produce a new instruction list so it's
going to just make your instructions
better and this the idea here is that
improve instructions would go in the
compiler right before you print out all
the instructions right so how do our
compilers work we parse we compile to
get an instruction list and then we
print out all the instructions right
that's the last step so let's imagine we
improved the instruction list before
printing it out let's just make it a
better instruction list so one way to do
this and this is where this is almost a
lot of what I'm telling you is the
simple thing is done in practice and
works so let's match the instruction the
instructions with and let's imagine that
at the front of the instruction list we
have an eye move of a reg offset with
EBP and some number N and the Reg ya X
followed by an eye move of reg ax and a
reg offset with the same the same number
there
and let me write this in the right
pattern ratcheting style okay so this
thing linked on to this thing linked on
to the rest of the instructions well if
we're moving EAX on to the stack and
then we're moving the value off the
stack back into EAX we know that which
instruction is redundant which
instruction is redundant the first
instruction of the second instruction
the second right we have to move it onto
the stack because we might look it up
later we definitely don't need to move
it back out of the stack into EAX right
now so we could take this and just turn
it into the first instruction here so
the I move with the Reg offset the first
one
linked on to rest instructions link
intereste answer so just drop the second
instruction in the instruction list
before printing should tweak this at all
to make it more useful like one tweak
here I could do to make this a little
more useful yeah call improve
instructions again right so I could
recursively call improve instructions
just on the rest just on the rest so
here I could do improve instructions on
the rest of the instructions yeah yeah
go for it ah interesting yet so yeah why
why is it that I didn't say anything
about these lead-up instructions so
what's going on here as I'm saying
and it's coming up in this recursive
call is we're saying we're just going to
process the instructions from the front
and if we get a prefix of instructions
here that we recognize that we can make
better we'll just we'll chop them off
we'll chop them off that answer your
question yeah so so we're talking about
this recursive call right now which I'm
sort of saying well okay so we're gonna
do this recursive call on the rest then
there is this question of like are we
dropping the first instructions what's
happening to the first instructions
right we have to talk about the
structure of this function a little bit
more so we're definitely going to recur
so that we can loop what else what else
we need to worry about yeah yeah
so we maybe could call improve
instructions on the whole thing right
because we might have crunched two
instructions together at the front that
then make another pattern match that we
could also improve right we might be
able to do that so maybe another
approach here is to call is to call
improve instructions on this whole thing
right so let's we definitely are making
the list smaller when we do this so we
don't have to worry about it being an
infinite loop because we as long as we
keep making a list smaller eventually
we'll get down to an empty list or some
list of the fixed size um but we could
just call it on this whole thing
maybe that shows some new pattern that
will work the real question here is what
to do if no pattern match but I think is
which i think is actually what's
underlying your question right because
what are we gonna do if we ran this
function on just this whole list it
would just say okay nope no matches
worked right you said it says move EBP
ESP at the top that has nothing to do
with the matches you suggested so the
thing we have to do is we need we might
have more cases where we know how to
improve the instructions here but we
need some ending case where we have some
instruction linked on to the rest of the
instructions and we say all right
nothing matched let's move forward in
the list so let's turn this into I
linked on to improve instructions unrest
because we're not going to be able to do
anything with that if it didn't match
any of the patterns that we could work
with so the idea here is exactly that
we'll loop through this whole list of
instructions and every time we find the
little prefix of them that we know how
to improve we'll shrink that and then
we'll see if we can do any better on
what's remaining so this is a very
specific very sort of like I guess blunt
is a good word for it there's a list of
instructions and we see instructions
next to each other that we can improve
let's improve them and put the new the
better instructions in place and the
idea here is that we're running a little
window we can think of this as a little
a little window along the sequence of
instructions and that's a little spot
where we're peeping in and trying to use
very very local information just about
two or three or four instructions at a
time to make things better just a little
bit and this idea has the name peephole
optimization and this is this is a super
common it's also relatively one nice
feature of this is that it doesn't
require understanding the entire rest of
the compiler some of those knows nested
matches required understanding a lot
about what each expression is supposed
to do and what errors it could have and
what tags it could have this you can
implement just by knowing what x86 is
supposed to do right you only need to
know about x86 to do this because you
just need to know that that can't this
second instruction can't possibly be
useful because it's just doing
unnecessary work so it's sort of
independent of the rest of the compiler
which is nice and it's a pretty much
just a loop over over the instructions
looking at a few that are next to each
other at a time yeah
so so let's keep in mind let's keep in
mind so your comment is accurate right
which is maybe we go through this whole
list and we don't find any instructions
to improve but I want to point out that
the time spent there is compile time not
run time right and that's pretty that's
that's actually an important distinction
in in all of this right that these
optimizations like matching more doing
something fancy with the tiling or doing
this people optimization is all costing
compile time and we're trading that
effort so that then the eventual program
runs faster the the example I often give
for this is if you were you know the
project manager for Firefox right you
would you should you can and should make
the trade-off that if you if someone
gave you an optimizing compiler that
took a week to run but made Firefox so
fast you can and should hire out servers
to compile Firefox for a week and then
the release that binary once that's
faster for your millions of users right
so that's your question is really good
because it gets it exactly that
trade-off right Mozilla should be happy
to run the fanciest peephole optimizer
in the world for a day if it saves me a
second right because I'm one of millions
of users all right so let's see so last
idea last idea I want to talk about
today is something that I think several
different areas of the room brought up
on on Monday when we were just talking
sort of brainstorming ways to improve
improve the compiler and there were
things like well like and this is
something that's come up in examples
I've drawn in class so the very first
programs we wrote were things like
and this was like back in week two or
three and a lot of you were like Joe I
know that that produces eight why did we
compile a binary right like that's not
you didn't accomplish much there by
compiling that program and then running
it and there's two observations to make
about this program one is that there's
an expression in here which is the
addition of two constants and there's
another slightly more subtle thing going
on here which is this is a use of a
variable whose value we know and I'm
putting know in quotes because we as
people did a lot of reasoning about this
to make sure we understood that we were
adding one in three that's not gonna do
anything like overflow right but X is
some variable and we know that its value
is going to be four there's no way its
value would not be four when we run this
program so there's two different things
going on here that we used as as
intelligent people to know that this
program is going to produce this answer
in fact one thing that sometimes happens
in the first couple programming
assignments in this course is folks
write compilers that are sophisticated
enough and they do this because they
probably implemented an interpreter in
CS c130 where if they compiled this
program let's just call this program P
for now
we compiled P sort of in the sense of
what's the best we can do for compiling
this program well it would be nice if we
could compile this program into move EA
x17 right because that's the
representation of of eight that would be
cool if when we compiled this program it
just turned into moving the answer into
EAX and there was actually a few of you
who did something like this I was kind
of it was actually kind of slowed you
down when you got to parse a handling
input because you couldn't handle all of
the unknown values that could be coming
into a program but for a program with
all known values we can actually write
into our compiler enough smarts so that
it can figure out what these constants
should be and generate much better code
for some of these cases and one way we
could do this is there a way we could do
this based on what we know so far way we
could do let's say maybe the green stuff
the +1 3 based on what we know so far
yeah
right so one idea one idea is is a good
idea to do instruction selection right
and we could say e prim to of + with an
Eden um and an enum this gets a special
compilation right maybe that just adds
the two numbers together and compiles to
a single move instruction so that's one
idea but it doesn't help us with this
other issue of this X variable whose
value we know so one of these things
seems like it might be an instruction
selection kind of thing but the other
one doesn't seem like it can be an
instruction selection kind of thing
especially if that X the use of that X
is sort of far away from where it's
defined but these are related ideas
because they both have to do with values
that we we know when we're compiling the
program have to be a particular value we
don't need to wait and run the program
to figure out what value they are so the
the there's an idea here that we can use
which is instead of writing instead of
making this part of the compile function
and in the spirit of what we just did
for people optimizations let's imagine a
function called improve expression that
takes an expression and produces an
expression that is better that is
shorter or has less fewer sub
expressions or does less work somehow
let's imagine we could write that
improve expression
the first case here is the one you
suggested that would be like the
instruction selection version of this
right which is well if we want to
improve EEPROM tools that have a plus in
the first position and then an eID numb
and 1 and E numb and - what's a better
version of this expression memory should
have type expression that's a better
version of this expression a better
expression to use than this one
we wanted a faster shorter way to get
the same result yeah so one suggestion
is move into EAX the + 1 + + 2 with some
string string fill in what's the issue
with that what's the issue with that
it's not a bad idea it's sort of the
same idea as the instruction selection
idea yeah yeah maybe there's some
shifting to do to it yeah what about
overflow are there other things anything
there's something there's something more
about how I decided to write this this
improve expression function I should
bother you about this yeah yeah we
simply wanted to return an expression
and if we start turning this into
instructions that's just gonna be like a
no camel level type error so I'm getting
it a different idea here than the idea
of picking instructions based on this I
want an expression I want something of
type expression yeah enum of + 1 + + -
that's pretty interesting right that's
pretty interesting I can take in an
expression and you know we'll do some
we'll do the usual recursive thing on
expression so we'll find any sub
expressions in other match cases here
but if we find something that's a
primitive that's a plus on it on two
numbers we can just replace that
expression with the number that's the
addition of those two things you just
replace it
we do have to worry a little bit about
overflow we might need to turn this into
something at an expression that throws
an overflow error if they overflowed but
if they don't overflow this is
definitely going to produce the same
answer that's pretty interesting that's
pretty interesting so what about this
other case this other case we talked
about and I'm going to make it a
slightly simpler case just to I'm gonna
imagine that there's a number in the
left not not some compound expression
but a number in the left let binding
position how could we improve that
expression how could we improve that
expression we know there's a number
there for X can we do to make that
better
yeah
so the suggestion is and we'll have to
think of the types make sense let's
imagine we have some helper you want to
replace all the instances of X with enum
of N in body where replace is going to
have to be some other helper function we
right
that's interesting
so that suggests that maybe we have this
other transformation we can do on
expressions which is if we know that a
particular identifier is always going to
be bound to the same value we could just
substitute it for that value everywhere
and we don't need the let anymore that
the job of the variable in the let was
to have a place for the value to live
after we evaluated it so we could look
it up multiple times but if we know what
value it is there's no reason to go
storing it and looking it up multiple
times we just use that value when we get
to it so if we can replace all the
instances of Eid X in the body with that
with that number expression then we get
to save time on looking up that variable
every time it's encountered and we never
have to store the variable in the first
place
so just to give the definition of these
things I think I'll talk a little bit
more about them on Friday this case is
called and mainly so if you want to look
them up this case is called constant
propagation you take constants and move
them to the